#### Karen A. Cranston

Biological Informatics Centre of Excellence Agriculture and Agri-food Canada Ottawa, ON karen.cranston@gmail.com

https://twitter.com/kcranstn http://kcranston.github.io http://github.com/kcranston http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4798-9499

I am an evolutionary computational biologist who is passionate about building computational tools and teaching skills to facilitate the adoption and practice of more efficient, reproducible science. As both project manager at a research facility and lead PI of Open Tree of Life (http://opentreeoflife.org), I have been both developer and manager of complex, multi-faceted software projects in evolutionary informatics. I am deeply involved as a teacher and leader in efforts to teach computation skills to scientists through The Carpentries (https://carpetries.org).

# Skill summary

*Technical*: extensive experience with python (web applications, libraries, scripting); knowledge of database (SQL) design, API design / implementation, UI design, Ansible deployment; previous experience with C / C++, PerI

Outreach / education: teaching interactive workshops, developing course material, coordinating training programs, and evidence-based instructor training; teaching technical and analytical skills to researchers; organization of hackathons for building tools and communities

Management: project and financial management of scientific research grants, supervising technical staff across multiple projects, agile software development, board member overseeing open source / open science organizations

Research: phylogenetic methods, including gene tree inference, visualization, supertrees; statistical genetics, particularly Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo

## **Education**

**PhD** (2007) Statistical Genetics. Department of Medical Genetics, University of Alberta, Edmonton, AB, Canada.

B.Sc., Honours, First Class (1996), Genetics. University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada

# **Employment**

**Technical Advisor, Bioinformatics** 

2017-present, Agriculture and Agri-food Canada, Ottawa, ON

#### Karen A. Cranston

Project manager and technical advisor in biological informatics group, leading development of software for biological specimen collection digitization and management.

#### **Research Scientist**

2015-2017, Department of Biology, Duke University, Durham, NC

Lead PI of Open Tree of Life (http://opentreeoflife.org) project that summarizes published phylogenetic trees into a synthetic tree of life; designing and writing software for storing, accessing and analyzing phylogeny data; leading hackathons and workshops; managing overall project, including software development.

#### Training Coordinator and Bioinformatics Project Manager

2010-2015, National Evolutionary Synthesis Center (NESCent), Durham, NC.

Management of informatics support for a broad range of evolutionary science projects; coordination of training programs in informatics and analytical skills for scientists; community building in open-source biodiversity and evolutionary informatics through hackathons and Google Summer of Code.

#### **Postdoctoral Research Associate**

2009-2010, Biodiversity Synthesis Center, The Field Museum, Chicago, IL

Interactive visualization of taxonomies and large phylogenies with Encylopedia of Life and iPlant Collaborative; summarizing large-scale gene tree incongruence across genomes

### **Postdoctoral Research Associate**

2007-2009, Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ PhyLoTA broswer, summarizing phylogenetic signal in GenBank; phylogenomic analyses of wild and domesticated rice species

### Laboratory technician

1997-2002, Cangene Corporation, Winnipeg, MB.

Maintenance of cell cultures; design and implementation of protein chemistry assays; analytical method validation.

**Technical writer** 1996-1997, Integrated Engineering Software, Winnipeg, Canada, 1996-1997 Technical documentation and online help systems for engineering simulation software.

## **Publications**

I have 19 peer-reviewed scientific papers, and 6 commentaries / preprints (noted with \*). Only papers from 2013-2018 shown below. Full list at http://kcranston.github.io/research/.

## Phylogenetic methods

McTavish, E. J., Drew, B. T., Redelings, B., & Cranston, K. A. (2017). How and Why to Build a Unified Tree of Life. BioEssays, 39(11). https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.201700114

Rees, J., & Cranston, K. (2017). Automated assembly of a reference taxonomy for phylogenetic data synthesis. Biodiversity Data Journal, 5, e12581. https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.5.e12581 Hinchliff, C. E., et al., (2015). Synthesis of phylogeny and taxonomy into a comprehensive tree of life. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 112(41), 12764-12769. http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1423041112.

### Software and databases

McTavish, E. J., et al., (2015). Phylesystem: a git-based data store for community curated phylogenetic estimates. Bioinformatics, btv276. http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv276 Ksepka, D.T., et al., (2015) The Fossil Calibration Database, A New Resource for Divergence Dating. *Systematic Biology*. http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syv025 Stoltzfus, A., et al., (2013). Phylotastic! Making tree-of-life knowledge accessible, reusable and

Stoltzfus, A., et al., (2013). Phylotastic! Making tree-of-life knowledge accessible, reusable and convenient. *BMC bioinformatics*, 14(1), 158. http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-14-158

## Open science, Collaboration, and Education

Stoltzfus, A., Rosenberg, M., Lapp, H., Budd, A., Cranston, K., Pontelli, E., ... & Vos, R. A. (2017). Community and Code: Nine Lessons from Nine NESCent Hackathons. F1000Research, 6. http://dx.doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.11429.1

Wilson, G., et al., (2017). Good Enough Practices in Scientific Computing. PLoS Comput Biol 13(6): e1005510 https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005510

Katz, D.S. et al., (2016). Report on the Second Workshop on Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences (WSSSPE2). Journal of Open Research Software. 4(1), p.e7. http://doi.org/10.5334/jors.85

Teal, T. K., et al., (2015) Data Carpentry: Workshops to Increase Data Literacy for Researchers. *International Journal of Digital Curation*. 10(1):135-143. http://dx.doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v10i1.351

Cranston, K. A., et al., (2014) Best Practices for Data Sharing in Phylogenetic Research. *PLOS Currents Tree of Life*. Jun 19. Edition 1.

http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/currents.tol.bf01eff4a6b60ca4825c69293dc59645

- \* Katz, D. S., et al., (2014). Second Workshop on on Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences (WSSSPE2): Submission, Peer-Review and Sorting Process, and Results. arXiv preprint http://arxiv.org/abs/1411.3464.
- \* Vision, T., & Cranston, K. A. (2014) Open data for evolutionary synthesis: an introduction to the NESCent collection. Nature Scientific Data. http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2014.30
- \* Cranston, K. A., et al., (2014): Simple rules for sharing phylogenetic data. figshare. http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.997763

Rodrigo, A., et al., (2013). Science incubators: synthesis centers and their role in the research ecosystem. PloS biology, 11(1), e1001468. http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001468

- \* Rees, J. A., et al., (2013): Response to GBIF request for consultation on data licenses. figshare. http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.799766
- \* Cranston, K. A., et al., (2013): A grassroots approach to software sustainability. figshare. http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.790739

# **Education and outreach**

- NESCent Academy: coordinated series of hands-on summer workshops in Evolutionary Biology and Informatics, 2010-2014.
- Software / Data Carpentry: Executive Council Chair since 2018; instructor certification in 2013; Instructor Training certification in 2017; co-lead development of reproducible science curriculum
- Phylogenetics workshops: taught phylogenetic methods and software in workshops at Wuhan Institute of Virology, Fudan University, Kenyan Medical Research Centre, The Field Museum, and Bodega Bay Marine Laboratory
- Hackathons: co-organized four hackathons on evolutionary informatics through NESCent and Open Tree of Life; see https://informatics.nescent.org/wiki/Main\_Page

## **Professional activities**

- Board of Directors: Open Bioinformatics Foundation (https://open-bio.org/), 2015-present
- The Carpentries Chair of Executive Council (http://carpentries.org), 2017-present
- Data Carpentry founding board member (http://datacarpentry.org), 2014-2017
- Organization administrator for NESCent Google Summer of Code participation, 2011-2013
- Program committee / panelist, Workshop on Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences (WSSSPE), http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk, 2013, 2014, 2016
- Society of Systematic Biology council, 2012-2014
- Systematic Biology Editorial Board, 2011-present
- Leadership team, Informatics for Evolutionary Biology (iEvoBio, http://ievobio.org) conference, 2013-2016
- Phyloinformatics Research Foundation board member, 2010-2016
- Team lead, iPlant Tree Of Life working group on Tree Visualization, 2009-2012
- Invited participant: iPlant Collaborative (http://iplantcollaborative.org) Grand Challenge Workshop on Assembling the Tree of Life to Enable the Plant Sciences, November 2009, Biosphere 2, Oracle, AZ

# Karen A. Cranston

- Journal referee for: Systematic Biology, Trends Ecology and Evolution, PeerJ, Nucleic Acids Research, Journal of Open Research Software, PLOS Computational Biology, Molecular Biology and Evolution. See Publons reviewer profile for recent activity.
- National Science Foundation grant review panelist, 2011 2014